Register of the William Hallam Tuck papers, 1914-1957
Hoover Institution Archives
William Hallam Tuck papers
1914-1957
62014
Tuck, William Hallam, 1890-1966.
8 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives. Stanford, California 94305-6010
Primarily consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Tuck's involvement in various relief effort organizations in the years surrounding World War II. The documents include materials generated by Tuck through his work with these organizations. The bulk of the material relates to his activities while serving with the United States Naval Reserve, and with various relief organizations following World War II, though a few materials relate to World War I relief work.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1962.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
William Hallam Tuck papers, 1914-65, Herbert Hoover Presidential Library and Museum, West Branch, Iowa
Commission for Polish Relief records, Hoover Institution Archives
Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930) records, Hoover Institution Archives
Commission for Relief in Belgium (1940-1945) records, Hoover Institution Archives
C.R.B. Educational Foundation records, Hoover Institution Archives
Finnish Relief Fund records, Hoover Institution Archives
First Aid for Hungary records, Hoover Institution Archives
Perrin C. Galpin papers Hoover Institution Archives
Hugh S. Gibson papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph C. Green papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Herbert Hoover subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Edward E. Hunt papers, Hoover Institution Archives
National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies records, Hoover Institution Archives
United States. President's Famine Emergency Committee records, Hoover Institution Archives
U.S. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
William Hallam Tuck was born on March 9, 1890, in Baltimore, Maryland, to Judge Somerville Pinkney Tuck and Emily Marshall Tuck. Tuck attended St. Paul School in Concord, New Hampshire, before going on to graduate from Princeton University in 1912. After briefly working as a chemical engineer, Tuck joined the Commission for Relief in Belgium (CRB) in 1915 before joining the British Army in 1916, where he served until 1918 with the rank of Captain Royal Artillery, B.E.F., attached to the 36th Brigade, Royal Australian Artillery.
When the U.S. entered the war, Tuck joined the U.S. Army in 1918, where he served as major in the 314th Field Artillery, 80th Division, and remained there until the end of the war. Afterwards, he resumed work with the CRB and stayed until 1922. During that time, Tuck developed a strong friendship with Herbert Hoover. He would later become heavily involved in Hoover's subsequent relief efforts, such as working with Hoover with the American Relief Administration. He was also a contributor to the fund initiated by Edgar Rickard in 1925 for the construction of the Hoover Tower at Stanford University.
After World War I, he became involved with Solway and Co. in various Belgian industrial and fiscal activities and represented this concern on the board of Allied Chemical and Dye Corporation, a U.S. based company, of which he also served as director. He married Hilda Bunge in Antwerp, Belgium, on April 20, 1920, with whom he had three children. He strongly supported Hoover during his presidential campaigns in 1928 and 1932. In 1936, he joined Hoover's Belgian American Educational Foundation, Inc. (BAEF), serving as vice president until 1966 and as comptroller from 1941 to 1950.
When war broke out in Europe in September 1939, in addition to serving in the BAEF, Tuck joined Hoover's then newly formed National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies. In 1940, he also served as representative of the Finnish Relief Fund, another Hoover relief effort. He worked heavily with the National Committee for Food for the Small Democracies from 1940 to 1941. His work with the committee was suspended when the U.S declared war against Japan and its allies.
During this time, Tuck also served with the United States Naval Reserve (USNR). In that capacity, he was heavily involved with the Military Government Training School. Following victory in Europe in May 1945 he participated in USNR committees such as the Economic Committee and the Post-Hostilities Committee. He served with the USNR until 1945, honorably discharged with the rank of Captain.
Following the end of World War II, Tuck remained active with Hoover's various relief organizations. His activities included involvement with Hoover's Food Mission of 1946-1947 and work with the International Refugee Organization, of which he would become director before resigning in 1949. Hoover also involved Tuck with the Second Hoover Commission on the Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government, where he served as executive director from 1953 to 1955. Honors Tuck received include Honorary Doctor of Philosophy degrees from the Universities of Louvain and Brussels. Prior to 1941, he also was named Commander of the following orders: the Legion of Honor of France, the Order of the Couronne of Belgium, the Order of Leopold II of Belgium, the White Rose of Finland, and the Orange Nassau of Holland. On August 28, 1966, Tuck died of a heart ailment in his summer home in Rougemont, Switzerland.
Resources
Biographical note for William Hallam Tuck, Herbert Hoover Presidential Library and Museum, http://www.ecommcode2.com/hoover/research/historicalmaterials/hmother.html
"William Hallam Tuck, Refugee official: Industrialist Also Was Aide to Hoover-Dies at 76", The New York Times, Wednesday August 31, 1966.
Scope and Content of Collection
The William Hallam Tuck papers primarily consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, and photographs, relating to activities of the Commission for Relief in Belgium (CRB) and American Relief Administration during World War I as well as World War II relief activities, such as the Finnish Relief Fund and the National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies. Also includes material related to the Belgian American Educational Foundation, Incorporated (BAEF), World War II Allied military government; and the world food survey of the Famine Emergency Committee, 1946.
Materials regarding activities during World War I are included, but the bulk of the material directly relates to his service with the United States Naval Reserve (USNR) during World War II and the various relief organizations during and following World War II.
The Biographical File includes speeches and transcripts of broadcasts. Also included are USNR related records and documentation such as correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other documents. Within the Biographical File, the documentation offers an American perspective on the events in Europe during the war and immediately following.
The Correspondence between Tuck and friends and colleagues relates to various relief organizations. Many of these correspondents were involved with the CRB, BAEF, and the National Committee for Food for the Small Democracies. These materials offer an insight into the activities of these relief committees, especially during the early days prior to the United States entry into World War II. Tuck's correspondents included Herbert Hoover and several members of Hoover's inner circle.
The Subject File includes reports, correspondence, memoranda, and printed materials generated through Tuck's work, and collected items. The bulk of the material relates to activities in Belgium, especially in the early days following its surrender to Germany during World War II. Also included are several records and memoranda from the BAEF and the National Committee for Food for the Small Democracies as well as a set of collected documents in English, French, and German pertaining to historical accounts of daily activities between World Wars I and II.
Photographs include two albums featuring members of the CRB, including Tuck and Hoover, and several images of Hoover following World War II.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930).; Commission for Relief in Belgium (1940-1945).; National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies.; Finnish Relief Fund.; American Relief Administration.; United States. President's Famine Emergency Committee.; Food supply.; International relief.; Military government.; Reconstruction (1939-1951); Russo-Finnish War, 1939-1940 Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; World War, 1939-1945--Finland.; World War, 1939-1945--Food question.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1916, 1940-1945, (bulk 1944-1945) (Box 1-2)
  Includes a Belgian-issued identification card, speeches and broadcasts, and documentation pertaining to Tuck's service in the United States Naval Reserve (USNR) including correspondence, orders received, memoranda, reports, and other documents. Also included are records pertaining to Tuck's work with the Military Government Training School in the European Affairs Division on Base II with the USNR. Arranged by document type.
  - Belgian-issued identification card, 1916 January 19 (Folder 1: 1)
    In German and French
  - Speeches and broadcasts, 1941-1942 (Folder 1)
    - Talk before the officers, Foreign Training School, Navy Department, Washington D.C., 1942 September 26 (Folder 1: 2)
    - "Town Meeting: Should Britain Relax Her Food Blockade for Hitler's Victims?", 1941 April 28 (Folder 1: 3)
      Includes published copy with other broadcasts from the meeting and typewritten transcription of Tuck's broadcast alone
  - United States Naval Reserve records, 1941-1945 (Folder 1-2)
    - Antwerp port, Documents regarding use of troops, equipment, and supplies, 1944 August (Folder 1: 4)
      Documents regarding use of troops, equipment, and supplies
    - Civil Affairs Division records, 1943-1945 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Correspondence, 1944 February - 1945 March (Folder 1: 6)
    - Economic Committee records, 1944 (Folder 1: 7)
    - History of Naval Affairs documents, 1944-1945 (Folder 1: 8)
      Task Organization document, curriculum vitae letter, Port of Antwerp related documents
    - Military Government Training School, Base II, 1944 December - 1945 (Folder 1: 9-11)
    - Military Government Training School, 1945 January 1 - March 31 (Folder 1: 12-13)
      First and Second Training Courses
    - Naval Activities in the European Theater of Operations records, 1945 February (Folder 2: 1)
    - Orders and personal papers, 1941, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 2)
      Included is background information Tuck provided about himself, including family information and past work experiences
    - Orders, 1945 May-April (Folder 2: 3)
    - "Non-Fraternization" document and Social Science Research Council materials, 1943, undated (Folder 2: 4)
    - Organizational charts, 1942, 1945 (Folder 2: 5)
      See also Oversize File, Box 11, Folder 1
    - Personal files and other documents, 1942-1943 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Post-Hostility Committee reports and correspondence, 1944 November-December, undated (Folder 2: 7)
    - Roster of Officers, 1945 March 1 (Folder 2: 8)
- Correspondence, 1915-1956, (bulk 1940-1941) (Box 2-3)
  Includes correspondence with various friends and colleagues. The bulk pertains to Tuck's activities during World War II with associates from the Belgian American Educational Foundation, Inc. and the National Committee for Food for the Small Democracies. Arranged into two subseries: alphabetical correspondence and chronological correspondence.
  - Correspondence, Alphabetical, 1934-1945 (Folder 2-3)
    - Burkhart, Gerald, October-December 1940 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Cajander, A.K, 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 10)
      Correspondence directly related to Finland
    - Campbell, Gerald, 1941 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Cudahy, John, 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 12)
      Some correspondence in French
    - Daniels, Tom, 10-27 December 1940 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Delano, William A., 7 February 1941 (Folder 2: 14)
      Letter also includes 4 photographs of the destroyed library at the University of Louvain after the German invasion in 1940
    - Duggan, Stephen, January-February, May, 1941 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Dunn, James, January, March, 1941 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Fonck, Charles, January-April, October, 1941 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Galpin, Perrin, 1945 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Gibson, Hugh, 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Henry, Bayard, Mrs., 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 20)
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1934, 1940-1941, 1945 (Folder 2: 21)
      See also Subject File, Box 6, Folder 12
    - International Refugee Organisation, Austria, 11 May 1949 (Folder 2: 22)
    - Joslin, Theodore, 1932 (Folder 2: 23)
    - Pate, Maurice, 1940-1941 (Folder 3: 1)
    - Pieters, Maurice, 1941 (Folder 3: 2)
      Some material in French
    - Richmond, Raymond S., 1941, undated (Folder 3: 3)
    - Smith, H. Alexander, 1940-1941 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Stevens, Lewis M., 1941 July, September (Folder 3: 5)
    - Strauss, Lewis, 1941 May-June, 1944 December (Folder 3: 6)
    - van der Straten Pontoz, Robert, Count, 1940 October (Folder 3: 7)
    - van Zeeland, Paul, 1940-1941 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Correspondence, Chronological, 1916-1956, undated, (bulk 1940-1941) (Folder 3)
    - 1916, 1918 (Folder 3: 9)
    - 1940 (Folder 3: 10)
    - January-April 1941 (Folder 3: 11)
    - May-December 1941 (Folder 3: 12)
    - 1942, 1956, undated. (Folder 3: 13)
- Subject File, 1914-1965, undated, (bulk 1940-1941). (Box 3-8)
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed matter pertaining to the organizations in which Tuck was an active participant. Also included are memoranda and reports pertaining to specific European countries and collected publications. Arranged alphabetically by document title or subject matter. Some materials are in French. See also Oversize File.
  - Asia, 1946-1947 (Folder 3: 14)
    Includes reports, studies, correspondence, and memoranda regarding the food situation in Japan and Korea post World War II. Correspondence includes a letter to the Assistant Secretary of War regarding the postwar reconstruction of Japan, 1947 March 5
  - American Relief Administration, World War I, 1919 (Folder 3: 15)
  - American Ordinance Corporation, 1939 July 17 (Folder 3: 16)
    Includes description and specifications for the 75 m/m mountain gun
  - "Les Avis, Proclamations, & Nouvelles de Guerre Allemandes", circa 1914 (Folder 3: 17)
    In French
  - Belgian American Educational Foundation Incorporated(BAEF), 1940-1945; 1956, undated (Folder 3-4)
    The bulk of the records have been arranged by type and content
    - Bound file, 1 of 2, October 1940; June-November 1945, and undated (Folder 3: 18-20)
      Includes cablegrams, correspondence, reports, memoranda, and other related documents collected and generated by the BAEF near the end of World War II. These documents came pre-bound and have been left in the original order.
    - Bound file, 2 of 2, June-November 1945 (Folder 4: 1)
      Includes cablegrams, correspondence, reports, memoranda, and other related documents collected and generated by the BAEF near the end of World War II. These documents came pre-bound and have been left in the original order. Some documents are in French
    - Cablegrams, correspondence, and transmissions, 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 2)
      Some documents are in French
    - Executive Committee meetings records, 1940 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Memoranda, 1940-1941, 1956, undated (Folder 4: 4)
    - Printed documents and collected items, 1940-1941, 1943, undated (Folder 4: 5)
    - Reports and notes, 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Belgian League of Honor records, 1938 (Folder 4: 7)
    Includes lists of elected officers from 1936, 1937, member lists, constitution, and by-laws
  - Belgium, 1916, 1940-1941 (Folder 4-5)
    - Bound File, 1 of 2, May-June 1940 (Folder 4: 8)
      Includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, and other related documents related to the Belgian food and political situation immediately following the surrender to Germany on 27 May 1940.
    - Bound file, 2 of 2, 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 9-10)
      Includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, and other related documents related to the Belgian food and political situation. The majority of the documents discuss the situation of getting supplies to the Belgian population following the surrender.
    - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Early occupation documents, May-June 1940 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Collected printed items, circa 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 13)
    - Memoranda and related documents pertaining to the food situation in occupied Belgium in bound file, May-July 1940 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Memoranda to the U.S. Ambassador for Belgium, 1940-1941 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Reports and announcements, 1916, circa 1940-1941 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Christian Weekly, 13-20 November 1940 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Commission for Relief in Belgium (CRB), 1915, 1916, 1919, 1940-1941, undated (Folder 5)
    - "Duties of the American Representatives in the Provinces", circa 1915-1919 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Extract of "CRB Reports & Publications" document, 1914 October-1918 April (Folder 5: 4)
    - "First Annual Report" document, 1914 November 1-1915 October 31 (Folder 5: 5)
      Part II ? Benevolent
    - Memoranda, reports, and miscellaneous documents, 1915, 1916, 1919, 1940-1941, undated (Folder 5: 6)
      Includes copy of a group portrait of CRB members taken in 1916 in Brussels (Tuck is the first row seated second from the left)
    - "Statistical Review of Relief Operations" by George I. Gay, 1925 June 20 (Folder 5: 7)
      Abridged version; includes a pullout map
  - Commission for Polish Relief, Inc., 1940-1941 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government, 1955 14 February - 27 June. (Folder 5: 9-10)
    Includes press releases
  - Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government, 1954-1955 (Folder 5: 11)
    Includes press releases, press conference, list of commission members
  - Community Service Society of New York first annual report, 1940 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Les crimes allemands d'après des témoignages allemands, 1915 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Cudahy, John, circa June 1940 (Folder 5: 14)
    Statement as ambassador to Belgium following the Belgian surrender to Germany
  - "Der Sieg der Alliierten (Fortsetzung),", 14 October 1918 (Folder 5: 15)
  - La Description de la cité d'Anvers, 1920 (Folder 5: 16)
  - "Excerpt from a letter from a noted scientist and Dutch patriot of Bergen, North Holland,", 12 January 1941 (Folder 5: 17)
  - Finland related documents, 1940-1941, 1946-1948. (Folder 5: 18)
    Includes reports, memoranda, bulletins, and other documents related to the food situation in Finland such as the famine emergency
  - Finnish Relief Fund documents, 1940 October (Folder 6: 1)
  - France related documents, 18 October 1918, 12 April 1941 (Folder 6: 2)
  - France related documents, 1914 (Folder 6: 3)
    "43 Ans de Politique Pacifique et Conciliant Envers l'Allemagne, 1971-1914"
  - Gibson, Hugh, 1940-1941 (Folder 6: 4)
    Cablegrams and correspondence pertaining to relief efforts in World War II
  - German Historians and Macedonian Imperialism booklet, 1921 July. (Folder 6: 5)
    Includes a note for Tuck from the author on the cover
  - "The German People Offer Peace" pamphlet, undated (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Grande carte des Étas-Unis d'Amérique" booklet, undated (Folder 6: 7)
  - Great Britain related documents, 27 June 1941 (Folder 6: 8)
    Britain To-Day, no. 56
  - Great Britain related documents, August-September 1914 (Folder 6: 9)
    Correspondence respecting the European Crisis, 1914 August, A Call to Arms, a speech by the Prime Minister, 4 September 1914, Mr. Lloyd George's Speech on the Road Hogs of Europe, 19 September 1914
  - Great Britain, February-March 1941 (Folder 6: 10)
    Documents generated by and regarding the British Embassy
  - La Guerre Mondiale: faits acquis à l'histoire, documents, 1915 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1940-1941, 1946 (Folder 6: 12)
    Includes correspondence between Hoover and Cordell Hull, then-Secretary of State in the Franklin Roosevelt administration from 1940 November to May 1941. Also includes pamphlet A Call to American Reason, 1941, and other documents related to activities post World War II. See also Correspondence, Box 2 Folder 24 and Oversize File Box 11 Folder 4
  - The Hoover Mission, delegation to Belgium, January 1941 (Folder 6: 13)
  - The Hoover Mission, "Some Notes on Trip with the Hoover Mission", Maurice Pate's notes for his trip with the Hoover Mission through Europe and Asia, March-June 1946 (Folder 6: 14-15)
  - Human Events, 17 February 1941 (Folder 6: 16)
  - An Impartial International Commission to Examine the Conditions Created by the Peace Treaties in the Danube Valley, maps included, circa 1921 (Folder 6: 17)
  - Intergovernmental Committee for European Migration, includes reports generated by the Committee, 1 May 1954 (Folder 6: 18)
  - Italy, draft for report regarding the food situation in Italy post World War II, 4 March 1946 (Folder 6: 19)
  - Latvia, 1948 (Folder 6: 20)
    Includes document by Alfreds Berzinsh
  - National Committee on Food for the Small Democracies, 1937-1965 (bulk 1940-1941), undated (Folder 6-7)
    Includes correspondence, reports, memoranda, reports generated for and by the committee and collected documents
    - Congressional records, 1941 2 May - 14 October (Folder 6: 21)
    - Correspondence and cablegrams, 1940-1941 (Folder 6: 22)
    - Internal records, 1940-1941 (Folder 6: 23)
      Includes internal policies, budget information, and member lists
    - Meetings, press releases, and speaker information, 1940-1941 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Memoranda, 1940-1941 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Notes and reports generated and collected, 1922, 1941-1945, undated (Folder 7: 3)
    - Printed materials and collected publications, 1937, circa 1940-1941, 1965 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Norway related document, undated (Folder 7: 5)
    "Norway's Food Situation"
  - Office of Military Government for Germany (U.S.), "Food position U.S. Occupied Areas of Germany" report, April 1946 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Office of Military Government for Germany (U.S.), Status Report on Military Government of Germany booklet, 15 March 1946 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Printed images of King Albert I and Queen Elizabeth of Belgium, 21 July 1918 (Folder 7: 8)
  - "Report on Survey of Hungarian Refugee Relief Problems in Austria", 15 January 1957 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Russischer und serbischer Kriegsschauplatz, by P. Krauss booklet, 1914 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Son Œuvre goûters scolaires, colonies de vacances, consultations de nourrissons, consultations prénatales, a publication by the Comité D'Assistance des Regions Libérées, undated (Folder 7: 11)
    Tuck was a member of this committee
  - Statement Regarding Food for the Small Democracies, 1940 (Folder 7: 12)
    Joint statement from the following organizations: The Commission for Relief in Belgium, Inc., The Norwegian Relief Fund, Inc., The Queen Wilhelmina Fund, Inc. (Holland), the Commission for Polish Relief, Inc.